Speaker 1: Senator
Hassan.
Speaker 2: Well, I want to thank the chair and ranking member for holding this hearing and to all of the panelists. Thank you for being here. Thank you for your work. I want to start with a question to Dr. McDougall. I've heard heartbreaking firsthand accounts from K-12 students in New Hampshire about their own struggles with mental health during the pandemic or their worries about their friends. Maybe the silver lining here
to
Speaker 2: follow up on what Dr. Skorton was just saying is that last week in a meeting with them in person I was tiptoeing around the issue. I wasn't sure fifth graders and high school students would want to talk to me about mental health. They had no inhibitions about talking to me about mental health. They are worried about it for themselves, for their friends, and the pandemic has really obviously exacerbated it. In 2020 mental health related emergency department visits for children
increased
Speaker 2: dramatically. And we know because of the pandemic, it's been harder for them to get in to see their primary care docs or to get to school in person to have the kind of mental health supports that school might provide. So we have to do better for our kids.
Speaker 3: Dr. McDougall, what steps can Congress take to ensure that pediatricians and primary care providers are prepared to respond to the pediatric mental health crisis we are experiencing
as a
Speaker 3: result of the pandemic? And what can we do in Congress to improve access to mental health services for kids through their
Speaker 3: communities, including their
Speaker 4: schools. - Very good question.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): As primary care physicians, we many times are the first persons who are talked to about the mental health concerns. And in some cases, we're able to manage the mental health concerns.
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that being said, typically it may involve a referral to a psychologist or a licensed social worker to work in concert with us. And someone mentioned earlier about the importance of telehealth. Congress has to continue funding of telehealth.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): That has to continue and we need to also prioritize training of licensed social workers, psychologists, and psychiatrists. So a strong message needs to be sent to our medical schools, our health profession schools, that this is a national crisis that we all need to step up to.
So
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): those are my initial thoughts.
Speaker 3: Thank you very much for those initial thoughts. They're great ones. I want to -- I'm just going to comment quickly that I thank
Speaker 2: all of the panelists for the support that you've all expressed for boosting the behavioral workforce and the workforce to treat substance use disorder. And I'm pleased and honored to work with Senator Collins on the Opioid Workforce Act, and we'll continue to push that through. Dr. Herbert,
Speaker 2: Under the American Rescue Plan, Congress increased federal funding for home and community based services to help more people access the care they need in the settings that best suits their needs. But this funding increase is temporary. Congress needs to make long term sustainable investments in the home health and community based workforce. That's
Speaker 3: going to ensure access to quality, comprehensive health services for older adults and individuals with disabilities who choose to remain in their homes.
Speaker 3: Doctor, can you speak to the role that home health workers play in improving care for older adults and individuals with disabilities,
Speaker 6: and how will additional sustained investments in home and community-based health workers strengthen our health care system? So
I
Speaker 7: think you nailed it. We need additional funding to support it. It's absolutely critical, the home health care workforce, in terms of maintaining the health, especially of our older populations. And if I, so I would simply support your assertion that the funding needs to continue post-COVID.
Speaker 7: Could I add something about behavioral health since you brought that up? I mean, as a clinical psychologist by training, I could go on for hours on this topic, but I'll try to just keep it very brief. It's absolutely critical that we train more behavioral health professionals. There's no question at all levels, not just doctoral level trained people, but master's level counselors, social workers. At the same time, what we also need to do is we, and this gets back to that interprofessional
Speaker 8: model I was talking about.
Speaker 8: we need to train all healthcare professionals, including dentists to recognize and OBGYNs for example, to recognize and diagnose behavioral health problems. And there are behavioral health interventions that those non-expert providers can also learn to provide. And also I would add that we've made tremendous progress over the past 30 years
Speaker 8: in non-pharmacological treatments that in many cases have longer lasting effects, but they're still not widely practiced. Because it's much easier to just give somebody a pill. And I'm not suggesting there aren't appropriate places for pharmacological
Speaker 9: prevention. - Sure, sure. No, I understand that, I appreciate that. And I realize I'm out of time. I'm just gonna say I'm gonna submit a question
Speaker 6: for the record.
Speaker 6: to the panel because, Mr. Chair, one of the things I think we really also need to focus on is a partnership between our primary care docs and community health workers to help address the social determinants of health. Because it's so critical if people, docs or treating, can actually get the nutrition assistance or housing that they need, that can be a big step forward too. Thank
Speaker 10: you. Thank
you.